foreign
[Music]
today we're going to talk about locust
bean gum what it is and how you use it
in ice cream so let's see how that
stands up against other stabilizers
we've talked about so far
[Music]
so this is a locust bean tree locust
bean gum which is also known as carob
gum is derived from the seeds of the
actual beans come from the tree
themselves and what happens is the bean
pods are removed they're dried
the actual seeds inside are then taken
out roasted
and powdered down into a white powder
much like all the other stabilizers we
talk about on here
like guagam Locus bean gum is also a
type of soluble fiber which uses a
thickening agent and a stabilizer in
lots of foods and especially ice cream
using locust bean gum in ice cream
helps to create a smoother creamier
texture and also prevents Ice Crystal
buildup
so with the Ice Crystal build up you
find that it will do that in your
freezer naturally so most frost-free
freezers these days that's difficult to
say has a freeze Thor cycle that stops
Frost building up inside the freezer
it's actually really bad for your ice
cream because the thawing and then
re-freezing enlarges your Ice Crystal
size
so good ice cream has lots of tiny
little ice crystals throughout and
they're so small that your tongue can't
pick them out and gives you a nice
creamy texture Bad Ice Cream has lots of
huge ice crystals in and you can taste
them and when you bite down into it you
can feel it on your tongue and your
teeth as well
[Music]
it's believed that by controlling the
free water in your ice cream base The
increased viscosity and shearing
movement of the churning process
combined with the stabilizers added
enables churned ice cream with
stabilizers to hold on to those small
crystals for much longer locust bean gum
is an excellent stabilizer but it has
poor gelling abilities and that's
actually a good thing when using it on
its own so gelling abilities of some
stabilizers something you may or may not
want in your ice cream depending on what
it is you're making and the types of
flavoring ingredients locus mean gum
does need to be fully hydrated between
75 and 85 degrees C and that's something
you might not want to do for your ice
cream base
locust bean gum is also commonly used
with Gua gum and carrageenans that is
our next video by the way Kerry ginnens
but now we're going to talk about
whether Locus bean gum is good or bad
for you
[Music]
generally as with all these stabilizers
that we're talking about everything is
completely safe but I can't talk as to
whether you personally will have a
reaction to a type of food so it's
something to be aware of if for some
reason you find that it doesn't agree
with you then stop using it as simple as
that there are lots of other stabilizers
you can use
there's also very little functional
evidence against these stabilizers
so don't let other content creators
scare you and there's himmongering also
now is lead on to vegetables where a lot
of them believe vegetables are bad for
you so if that's the kind of mentality
you have maybe avoid these
so you've decided that you want to use
or try Locus bean gum on your ice cream
what I would do is start with your
atypical normal amounts for a stabilizer
so 0.1 percent up to around 0.3 percent
a 0.3 is quite a lot of stabilizer but I
wouldn't go any higher than that if
you're going to use Locust beam gum on
its own normally looks been Gum as I
said before is added to things like Gua
gum and carrageenan so if you want to
add it to guagam then I do a 60 40 ratio
go six percent go on 40 locust bean gum
if you just use locust bean gum on its
own it can weigh off and that's when
it's melting so what weighing off is is
the liquid within your ice cream base
will separate from the fats and you'll
get this clear liquid in the bottom of
your bowl that is the way coming off and
that's an effect from just using too
much Locus bean gum if you are getting
weighing off when you when using logos
being gum on its own then add some guar
gum to it to help stabilize that mixture
like a puzzle ice cream and stabilizers
once all the pieces are together the
result is just outshines all other
store-bought ice cream
so when using ice cream stabilizers make
sure you add them to your sugar Stir It
All really well together before adding
it to your warming base or your cold
base depending on what stabilizer you're
using and then I make sure that no
clumping occurs well that's all we've
got for locust bean gum today thank you
very much for joining me as normal as
you can see behind I'm still ghost Lake
in Alberta it's overcast today but there
is a seaplane on the water so that's
something you don't see every day next
week we're going to talk about
carrageenans there's three different
types and they have three different
times and places to use so stick around
if you want to know more about ice cream
stabilizers and how to make ice cream
importantly a couple of weeks away from
getting the first ice cream make in our
new house up and running so thanks so
much for watching don't forget to like
And subscribe and I'll see you next time
thank you